You will hear a potter, Heather McCallum, speaking to a group of people who are visiting
a pottery, a place where people make pots and other objects from clay.
First, you have some time to look at questions 11 to 16.
You will hear a potter, Heather McCallum, speaking to a group of people who are visiting
a place where people make pots and other objects from clay.
Then, you have some time to look at questions 12 to 16.
You will hear a potter, Heather McCallum, speaking to a group of people who are visiting
a place where people make pots and other objects from clay.
Now listen carefully and answer questions 11 to 16.
Hello and welcome. My name's Heather McCallum and I'm one of the potters who work here at
Edelman Pottery. Before we go into the workshop, I just want to say a bit about the craft of
pottery. Then we'll have a look at the equipment and you can try making a pot of your own.
Like many people, I'm sure you know that pottery as an art form is tens of thousands of years
old and we know this because it stands the test of time. Things like baskets and pictures
don't survive in the earth in the same way that pots do and even if ancient pots are
found in small pieces, they still provide a lot of information about the past.
There's no doubt that pottery has given archaeologists a fascinating insight into how ancient humans
The shape of an artefact may have been lost, but archaeologists can tell whether the pots
were for, say, storage or cooking by examining the impressions on the clay, the scratches
from tools, and the clay itself can reveal where the pots came from.
When I ask people why they want to take a pottery class with me, they sometimes talk
about these things. Like our ancestors, they hope that something they create will also
last longer than they do, that their work, whether it is good or not, might say something
about humanity many years after their death.
Of course, you will all have your own reasons for coming here. As far as I'm concerned,
what I love most is the concentration you need to make a good pot. That focus takes
you away from the stresses of everyday life. If you're elderly, it's also good exercise
for hands and wrists and helps with arthritis. And of course, it's a fun activity for children
because it's so messy. Here at Edelman Pottery, we show you some of the basic pottery techniques
so that you can use these to create whatever you wish, a gift for a friend perhaps. Like
nearly everyone who comes here, I'm sure this is the first time you will have tried the
art, so we'll keep things simple today.
Now, before we move on, can I just say a word about what you're wearing? As we said
in our email, please remove any watches, necklaces, etc. and put them somewhere safe. If you have
long hair, do tie it back now. We'll provide aprons later, but I trust your clothes are
old but comfortable, not your favourite t-shirt or jeans.
Before you hear the rest of the talk, you have some time to look at questions 17 to 20.
Now listen and answer questions 17 to 20.
So now we're in the workshop. Have a look around. There's a lot going on. To make pottery
that will last, you need a potter's wheel, a kiln, which is basically a very hot oven
where you fire the pottery, and some tools. So first, the kiln. If you look over in the
far corner, you'll see one of ours. Since their invention, kilns have changed very little,
though in the past 20 years, a lot of progress has been made in temperature control. Basically,
a kiln removes the water from clay at temperatures of around 1000 degrees Celsius. This allows
anything you've made to set permanently in shape. It's a pretty ugly, heavy object that's
hard to keep in a house or flat, so most people don't have one. You may think, can't I use
my oven? Well, that's possible, but domestic ovens don't really get hot enough, and eventually
the clay will crack and fall apart. Some people fire pottery in a fire pit outside, but bear
in mind that can be dangerous. You also need to know about safety procedures for kilns
as they release toxic compounds into the air. Every potter needs a potter's wheel.
This machine is used to shape the clay into an object with circular walls or sides, such
as a bowl. Its invention revolutionised the pottery industry, allowing multiple items
to be produced in a day. Lastly, there are a number of different tools that potters use,
depending on what they want to make. When you start, your hands can make all kinds of
shapes and curves without relying on a sculpting tool. However, there are some basic tools
that you will need to handle the clay on the wheel. Some look very strange and have
even odder names that you may find hard to remember. Rather than go through them all
now, I'll just name a few tools as we go along. We can provide these, and I wouldn't recommend
spending money on them yet. So, let's try making a pot of your own. If you sit down...
That is the end of part 2. You now have 30 seconds to check your answers to part 2.
Thank you for watching.